for Pacifica Radio September 1st 2019
I'm Scott Horton this is anti-war radio
[Music]
all right you guys welcome to show it is
anti-war radio I'm your host Scott
worden I'm the author of the book fool's
errand time to end the war in
Afghanistan and I'm the editorial
director of anti-war calm you find my
full interview archive at Scott Horton
org more than 5,000 interviews for you
now going back to 2003 all right you
guys introducing John Kiriakou he is the
only CIA officer to go to prison over
the Bush era torture scandal of course
for confirming the names of a couple of
CIA officers involved in it not for
torturing anybody he would have gotten
out of jail free for that no problem
anyway here he is writing at consortium
news.com and the article is called in
search of a Russia Gate scalp the
entrapment of Maria boo Tina welcome
back to the show how you doing John
thanks good to be with you
very good to have you here yeah Russia
Gate scalp that's a good way to put it
the Maria boo Tina she looks a lot like
Anna Chapman so you're trying to tell me
that she's not a Russian spy after all
what's the deal that imagine that and
you know the mainstream media CNN MSNBC
even Fox when they refer to her they
always refer to refer to her as either
Russian spa.i or convicted Russian spy
Maria boo Tina and that's just simply
factually wrong she's not a spy she was
never accused of being a spy
she was never charged with spying she
was charged and convicted of conspiring
to fail to fill out a form literally
that was the that was the crime well and
I think as you talked about in
article here she may have forgotten to
fill out the form but there was never
any evidence of a conspiracy to fail
that fill out the form that's the funny
part of this - um they so wanted to wrap
her up in some kind of an espionage case
that what the FBI did is they recruited
a guy named Patrick Byrne Patrick and in
the interest of transparency I know
Patrick Byrne we're not friends but
we're acquaintances and we traveled
together for several months during the
Gary Johnson campaign in 2016 I like
Patrick he's a good guy I had no idea
that he was secretly an FBI informant at
the time but what they did was they
recruited Patrick Byrne and they said
this is the CEO of famously the the
former now CEO of overstock.com zone
heir and libertarian ish as you say
they're mentioned Gary Johnson fellow
traveler with libertarian party types
yeah and who famously was on TV in the
last couple of weeks spilling his story
and there was a conservative journalist
who he had spoken to previous to those
TV interviews I forget her name I'm
sorry but who had done a big write-up on
his story about his involvement with
poutine oh that's right and why was he
involved why was he involved with the
FBI because he was a patriot he
considered himself to be a patriot he
said the FBI approached him because he
had already done some work with them
that he didn't want to talk about and
they said okay here's what we want you
to do we want you to approach this
Russian woman Maria boo Tina and want we
want you to strike up a friendship slash
relationship with her so he did and then
he reported back to the FBI and he said
yeah she's just a grad student she's not
a spy she's not trying to infiltrate the
the Trump campaign or the government
she's a gun nut and she's trying to
broker good relations between the NRA
and whatever the NRA equivalent is in
Russia but she's not a spy and the FBI
told him and this is according to his
own
interviews everywhere on CNN on MSNBC on
Fox he says that James Comey and Peter
struck and one other FBI official who he
did not want a name told him they
directed him to go back to Betina and to
initiate a sexual relationship with her
which he did he began having sex with
her and then when she was arrested and
charged with failing to fill out the the
foreign alien Registration Act form on
the Internet the prosecutors
disingenuously falsely went to the press
and said she traded sexual favors in
exchange for access that was a lie the
truth was that the FBI told him to have
sex with her yeah and what boy did they
smear her as you know uh an attractive
Russian woman so therefore this is a
honeypot this is a trap this is how the
agent of Putin sent here to suborn the
Republicans and of course they all fell
for it that is exactly what happened the
fix was in from the beginning and let me
tell you another thing and I do say this
in the in the peace and consortium news
I've become very well acquainted with
federal sentencing schedule this crime
is one of the most minor felonies that a
person can commit it ranks up where up
there with the great crimes like making
a false statement okay so the federal
sentencing guideline for a first-time
offender is zero to six months what most
people get and actually it was hard to
find this because really nobody's ever
prosecuted for failing to fill out this
form
well the backup behind it tell us this
foreign agents Registration Act explain
because you have a paragraph in here
about you one time represented a foreign
government for a minute there yes yes
the foreign affairs Registration Act was
written in 1938 what was happening in
1938 was that the federal government was
afraid of German Americans representing
German interests later Nazi Party
interests in the United
dates and they wanted to make it
transparent so if you were taking money
from the Nazi Party or from the Kaiser
you had to register and so the Justice
Department would know that you were
acting on behalf of the Kaiser or later
on behalf of the Nazi Party and so the
law has been on the books for a very
long time but it is almost never
enforced the purpose of the law is
frankly just to keep a list of lobbyists
so if you're hired by I had the
government of XYZ to do some work
whether it's to lobby Congress or or
Lobby the media you know write articles
whatever that way the American people
can go online and search the fair
database and say okay Scott is lobbying
for the government of Zimbabwe okay I
say in the article that back in 2008 I
was hired very briefly for a matter of a
couple of months but the government of
Abu Dhabi they hired me to write for op
eds
in support of doing business in the
United Arab Emirates specifically in Abu
Dhabi so I wrote the for op eds they
paid me a few grand I went to the fara
database and I said I'm John Kiriakou I
took five grand for from the government
of Abu Dhabi and I wrote these four
op-eds and I put links and there I'm
done I heard as a foreign agent by the
way anyone who shocked that I would
represent the government of Zimbabwe let
me tell you they paid me a hundred
trillion dollars how could I turn it
down but the problem is is it didn't bob
ways so anyway it's you know people get
tripped up over the over the word agent
and all it is is all it means is that
you're acting on behalf of that of that
country so the feds in the case of
Bettina alleged that she was acting on
behalf of Russia that she had been
directed by the Russian government to to
try to create a relationship between
Russian gun clubs and the NRA well she
never admitted that but the
preponderance of the evidence I suppose
showed that she was she was probably or
made
we have acted on behalf of the Russian
government blah blah blah and so they
got her for not filling out the form but
when you don't fill out the form and
you've never been convicted of a crime
before the normal sentence is 18 months
of probation but she didn't get 18
months of probation she got 18 months in
prison now the federal sentencing
guideline for a maximum sentence is 0 to
6 months she didn't get 0 to 6 she got
18 months in a federal prison so that
just goes to show you how political this
whole thing was hey guys Scott here for
liberty under attack publications
looking for a Liberty focus publisher
Liberty under attack publishes books and
strategy guides for individuals looking
to increase their personal freedom
they assist authors through the entire
publishing process proofreading editing
cover designs paperback and Kindle
formatting and full audio book narration
and post-production Tom Scott sent you
and get 20% off a full-service deal to
get some one-of-a-kind books or for more
information visit Liberty under attack
comm hey guys check out listen and think
audiobooks there listen and think calm
and of course on audible.com and they
feature my book fool's errand time to
end the war in Afghanistan as well as
brand new out inside Syria by our friend
Reese Erlich and a lot of other great
books mostly by libertarians there Reese
might be one exception but essentially
they're all libertarian audiobooks and
here's how you can get a lifetime
subscription to listen and think
audiobooks just donate $100 to the Scott
Horton show at Scott Horton org slash
donate you know we know from Jim
Bamford's great work in The New Republic
the spy who wasn't he wrote about her
that as you say she really was trying
essentially to expand gun rights in
Russia and was seeking the advice of
American right-wingers for helping to
get that done and then secondary to that
was just hoping to see like a great many
private American citizens to better
relations with Russia and yet just like
in the Muller report this supposedly is
itself nefarious why would you want to
seek better
so that Russia can control and destroy
America more and better and it's all
just question begging crazy conspiracy
nonsense we're in fact what you have
instead is American patriots who
recognize that the Soviet Union hasn't
existed for quite some time now and that
maybe we can figure out a way to as the
president says get along with Russia how
crazy is it right or how crazy do our
leaders have to be to want to use
diplomacy to improve relations with our
adversaries that's virtually treasonous
if you listen to the to the Democratic
National Committee these days you know I
used to complain about the George W Bush
administration all the time I was still
at the CIA during the George W Bush
administration and I used to say that I
had never seen an administration works
so hard to not talk to our adversaries
well there's been this weird role
reversal now where any time the
administration the current
administration wants to talk to an
adversary rather than to send troops or
carrier battle groups the Democrats jump
up and down but we can't have diplomacy
with North Korea we can't have diplomacy
with Russia or China
that's treasonous no that's diplomacy I
mean listen even the Bush Doctrine this
is the Cheney doctrine you don't that
would be distinguishing and granting
Authority and stature and credibility to
these terrible people were we to even
share a room with them at any time so
we'll just have to wait till the war
comes that's it that's it and what's
happening is we're becoming
compartmentalized and and divided even
more than we have in the past and we're
getting to the point where we just we
just don't trust anything we hear or see
yeah but you know it should and that
much is fair I mean they lie to us so
much but it fault then should be still
regardless of which party we're talking
about should always be against war and
for diplomacy and the fact that anyone
could let partisanship blind them to a
truth like that Donald Trump
is the DMZ and people complain about
that yeah there can be great but 100%
unanimity by 320 million Americans that
that's the best thing he's ever done in
his entire stinkin life it's bizarro
world where everything is opposite like
in this in the Superman comics we want
the President to go to to the DMZ we
want the President to negotiate with the
leaders of countries with which we don't
get along we want there to be new arms
agreements that that limit the
production the manufacturing of these
dangerous weapons that's that's exactly
what all Americans should be agreeing on
that shouldn't be a partisan you know
meme that ends up popping up on on
Facebook yeah
all right now so back to Murray abou
Tina here and you're the way you talk
about it shadow of a doubt forget about
it she was never an agent of the Russian
state sent here to do anything other
than what was obviously aboveboard but
two things there first of all didn't she
have this powerful Russian patron who
was a former central banker type guy
wink wink former and so isn't that
relevant and does that have something to
do really with the possibly a actual you
know a more real role that she was
playing sort of behind the scenes in a
way or that's just a red herring
yeah because even in non-official cover
cases and let's let's pretend that Maria
boo Tina was a Russian spy she would be
what's called a knock a non-official
cover agent and that means that she
would not have been working out of the
Russian embassy with diplomatic immunity
she would have been a private citizen
without diplomatic immunity so let's
pretend that that's all true
even if she were a non-official cover
officer she would not have been
reporting back through a banker or a
so-called oligarch or an NGO or whatever
she would have had a governmental
handler and if the FBI is on every
Russian in Washington like white on rice
like they tell us that they are
they would have been able to patch that
together and they didn't not only did
they not but she was never even accused
of having been a non-official cover
actor not even accused so I think it's a
red herring you know you see in the
media all the time this is one of these
things that drives me crazy you see that
anytime anybody falls under suspicion
they have ties to fill in the blank and
they have ties to somebody who's always
and I use this in air quotes close to
Putin well what the heck does that mean
every Russian name that we read in every
American newspaper or every news website
has ties to Putin
what kind of ties to Putin are you
saying the person is a spy he's the
president of the country they live in so
it's like your ties to Donald Trump and
mine exactly correct yes and the thing
is as Americans we don't ask those
questions we read these articles we say
oh well she's tied to you know boris and
Natasha they have ties to Putin and we
just accepted as fact hmm and just like
all good conspiracy theories each part
of the conspiracy theory also is a
conspiracy theory and they all rely on
each other to be true and so boo Teena
we know she's a spy because of the rest
of the Russia gates scandal going on and
we know that the rest of the Russia gate
scandal going on here is a thing because
of Maria butene she's one of the pieces
that make it all true there you go yeah
I used to say it's the self licking ice
cream cone you can hear the Scott
Wharton show an anti-war radio on
Pacifica 90.7 FM KPFK
in LA KPFK org APs radio at ApS radio
comm the libertarian Institute at
libertarian Institute org and of course
check out the full archives more than
5,000 interviews now going back to 2003
and sign up for the podcast feed at
Scott Horton org and thanks san time war
radio I'm talking with John Kiriakou now
so here's the real flip side of this is
that
the CIA and the FBI America's secret
police they decided to do I don't know
people calling it a soft coup it seems
like a pretty hard coup against the
major party nominee for president you
knighted States then the president-elect
and the President himself and it happens
to be a bunch of FBI counterintelligence
officers that you are familiar with who
did these indeed indeed when I was
working for the Senate Foreign Relations
Committee in 2011 I was approached by a
Japanese diplomat who offered me money
in exchange for trade secrets and I told
him he should be ashamed of himself and
I went directly to the office of the
Senate security officer and I reported
that I had been pitched by a foreign
intelligence officer so the Senate
security guy called the FBI the FBI sent
two young agents up to interview me and
they said here's what we want you to do
we want you to call the guy back we want
you to take him to lunch and try to get
him to tell you exactly what information
he wants and how much money he's willing
to pay for it I did that and I wrote
them a memo with all the details and
they asked me to do it a second time and
a third time and a fourth time and I did
because I'm a patriot a year later I'm
called by the FBI
she just had lunch with him over and
over again making promises but never
actually finishing any kind of deal
correct correct
I just strung him along the whole time a
year later the FBI calls me and they
said you remember that case you helped
us with a year ago I said sure they said
well something else came up and we need
your help and I said and these were my
exact words because I'm a fool I said
anything for the FBI I went down to FBI
Washington field office headquarters and
I met by two FBI agents we went over
this Japanese case and then they started
asking me other questions it was an
hour-plus into the interview before I
realized that they're investigating me
and I said wait a minute wait a minute
am i under arrest and the guy says not
yet but you should know that we're
raiding your house right now as we speak
I said I want to see my attorney I got
up I started to walk out and I'm blocked
by a guy named Peter struck and Peter
struck says to the two FBI agents tell
me he implicated himself and one of them
says not really no and I said again am i
under arrest
struck says not today and I walked out
Peter struck arrested me
the following Monday that was a Thursday
he arrested me on Monday now the FBI
likes to make its arrest on Thursdays
because federal prisoners are not
arraigned in Washington on Fridays so
you spend Thursday night Friday night
Saturday night and Sunday night in the
DC jail getting the daylights beaten out
of you and then finally you're arraigned
on Monday morning well after that arrest
we got discovery and in discovery we
learned that there never was any
Japanese diplomat he was an FBI agent
undercover trying to get me to commit
espionage because they had no espionage
case against me and they had already
made a political decision that they
wanted to charge me with espionage
that's what they've done with Maria boo
Tina in other words you weren't even
going to meet with this guy at all
except on their instruction in the force
and not and not that they were stringing
you along other than they were telling
you that you were working for them
investigating this guy correct I only
did it because they asked me to do it
and it was in other words this isn't
like if you take the parallel with like
one of these you know fake terrorism
case entrapments they trap the guy into
agreeing to break the law and do
something wrong I don't know of any
where they entrap the guy by making him
think that he's acting as an undercover
agent for them helping enforce the law
against another guy who also is working
for the government no not at all what so
this is a real this is real real
entrapment oh this was real entrapment
what they wanted me to do was to lie in
the memos that I was writing them and
say yeah you know what in this in this
meeting he didn't offer me any money
when in fact he had offered me five
thousand ten thousand and they
wanted me to put it in my pocket so they
could arrest me for espionage and for
actually taking the money but I didn't I
kept reporting back every detail of
those meetings right back to the FBI and
then there's a memo I found from one of
the FBI agents to Peter struck we got
this in discovery and the FBI agent says
we should probably end this operation
he's obviously not going to take the
bait and then they shut it down and you
have that in writing oh yeah this
Japanese diplomat told me in our last
lunch that he had been promoted he got
his dream job and he was going to become
the number two in the Japanese embassy
in Cairo I congratulated him I shook his
hand and I never saw him again amazing
so well go back then to 2016 and and I
guess your view of his role with Jimmy
and for that matter were John Brennan in
getting this whole Russia Gate hoax
going in the first place oh you bet
so you remember back in 2017 the debate
was was there spying against the Trump
campaign and Peter stroked at all
maintained that there wasn't spying
there were inquiries because there were
allegations that there was some kind of
a connection between the Trump campaign
and Russia
that's nonsense whether there was let's
even pretend that there was a connection
between the Trump campaign in Russia you
don't then begin electronic surveillance
against a major Party presidential
campaign what you do and this has
happened in the past is the director of
the FBI or the director of the FBI's
field office either in Washington or New
York will go to the chairman of the
campaign and say listen you guys have a
problem there's somebody in your
campaign who's talking to a foreign
government
that's what normally happens but what
happened in 2016 and we're not talking
about Jill Stein or Gary Johnson here
we're talking about the Republican Party
nominee who's got flip a coin
essentially a 50-50 chance of being the
next president of the United States and
this is something that David Stockman is
said all along that that is all you need
to know
to know what a put-on this whole thing
is that if they thought for a moment
that oh no the Russians are attempting
to make inroads into a campaign and they
were not the ones setting it all up in
the first place they would have ran
straight to trump to warn him that would
have been their obligation their
overriding obligation yes that unless
they really thought he was leading it
all but they had no reason to claim that
based on them setting up Carter page and
George papadopolis I mean come on
and and you know the the FBI owes an
apology a public apology to Carter page
at the very least I mean look at look at
the the wrongs that were committed here
you've got Carter Page who was utterly
innocent of any wrongdoing and not only
did they take out a FISA warrant against
this guy to to intercept all of his
electronics but they renew it three
times knowing that the evidence that
they're using is specious knowing that
that report was no good that it was all
hearsay so number one they dropped the
ball there number two don't forget that
Peter Strock wasn't just some FBI agent
who hated Trump Peter struck was the
director of the FBI's division for
counterintelligence this guy wielded
incredible authority he was the FBI's
mole hunter well if the mole hunter is
telling his adulterous girlfriend that
he's going to take down this president
if he wins you've got another problem so
you know it seems to me that we're not
talking here about just bad form on the
part of Peter struck we're talking about
potential criminal activity or even if
it doesn't meet the threshold of
criminal activity we're talking about
conspiracy to commit criminal activity
yeah I think we need to look at him so
let's get back to her now so Bob Muller
did not prosecute her someone must have
brought him this case and he said now I
don't worry whoever was running his
so-called investigation over there said
yeah no I don't think we're gonna go
with this this is you know too low to
even I mean these are the same people
who prosecuted Mike Flynn but they
didn't go for this and they let some
other
loser attorney at the DOJ do it instead
it still made a great talking point on
TV though oh yes yeah well you know this
is the sad truth that is that the fix is
in and there are so many different
people so many different layers of
bureaucracy that are involved the fix is
in I've been I've been repeating in
interviews this past week something that
one of my attorneys told me and it bears
repeating here I had received an offer
from the Justice Department this was
their best and final offer
for two and a half years in prison I do
23 months and I make the whole thing go
away and this isn't for the entrapment
this is for the leaking of the CIA names
right correct one name and I didn't even
leak it I confirmed it and it was never
made public right but like I say the fix
was in
so I thought about it literally all
night long my wife and I stayed up all
night long and I decided the next
morning I was going to turn the deal
down I hadn't done anything wrong there
was no harm to the national security I
had no criminal intent I was going to
turn it down and one of my lawyers got
very angry at me and he said to me you
know what your problem is
your problem is you think this is about
justice and it's not about justice it's
about mitigating damage take the deal
and I came to realize that all of these
cases are about mitigating damage
they're not about justice nobody cares
if you're innocent nobody cares about
the degrees of guilt
nobody cares about criminal intent what
happens is people at the Justice
Department get promoted people at the
FBI get promoted only when you are
successfully prosecuted so you're going
to jail you know the the the Justice
Department
according to Pro Publica wins ninety
eight point two percent of its cases
that's not an accident that's a result
of plea bargains because they heap so
many charges on you they threaten you
with so many years behind bars I was
looking at forty five years in prison
and they offered me twenty three months
so what are you gonna do you're gonna
roll the dice knowing that you have a
one
point eight percent chance of winning
are you just gonna take the deal and
make the thing go away yeah it's no
accident that most of these cases are
heard in the Eastern District of
Virginia which is in Alexandria that's
the home of the CIA it's the home of the
Pentagon
I hired Oh Jay Simpsons jury consultant
and he flew up from Dallas and he said
look if we were in any other district in
America I'd say let's go for it we're
gonna win this thing but the Eastern
District of Virginia he said your jury
is going to be made up of people from
the CIA the FBI Department of Homeland
Security Department of Defense
intelligence community contractors you
don't have a prayer he told me take the
deal no we saw the way they did Jeffrey
sterling where exactly didn't even
really attempt to demonstrate that he
had passed these secrets to James rice
into the New York Times instead they
just said well it seems as though I'm
not sure they prove it seems as though
they had called each other but they only
know connections and numbers I don't
really know who was on the line they
don't you know and they had no more
information than that other than on on
sometimes it seems as though they may
have talked on the phone and that was
enough to get a conviction beyond a
reasonable doubt
so yeah they called it prosecution by
metadata yeah that's all they had was
the metadata and in fact in the sterling
case at the same time sterling had filed
a racial discrimination lawsuit against
the CIA that that Rison was covering for
the New York Times right so of course
they were talking so in others they had
a perfectly plausible explanation for
why they were on the phone other than
passing secrets yes exactly exactly
it sounds like reasonable doubt but I'm
from Texas that's what I would call
thank you so much for your time on the
show today John really watch it all
right you guys that's John Kiriakou
and he wrote this for consortium
news.com in search of a Russia Gate
scalp the entrapment of Maria boo Tina
of course former CIA officer and author
of The Reluctant spy I'll write you guys
and that has been anti-war radio for
this morning I'm your host Scott Horton
the author of fool's errand time to end
the war in Afghanistan
an editorial director of anti-war calm
you can find my full interview archive
at Scott Wharton org more than 5,000
interviews for you now going back to
2003 I'm here every Sunday morning from
8:30 to 9:00 on KPFK 90.7 FM in LA see
you next week
[Music]